[speaker-0] you
[speaker-0] Welcome to the lighter side of the
spectrum, a podcast where we explore how
to find
[speaker-0] joy, connection and growth while
navigating the challenges of parenting
kids and
[speaker-0] teens on the autism spectrum. Remember
that inclusion and hope are key to making
[speaker-0] life better for everyone and that even in
the most challenging moments, there's
[speaker-0] always a lighter side. Now here's your
host, David Kaufer.
[speaker-0] Hey everyone, welcome to another episode
of the lighter side of the spectrum. Glad
[speaker-0] you can join us. I am so excited today
because I have a good friend and a very
[speaker-0] knowledgeable guest, Andrew Millevojvich.
Did I get it? Did I get it, Andrew? You
[speaker-0] nailed it. All right. All that practice
paid off. But let me give you a little
intro
[speaker-0] to Andrew. He provided this and I'm going
to spice it up because I do that in
[speaker-0] marketing. But Andrew is...
[speaker-0] husband to an awesome wife and father of
two great young adults, an engineer and
[speaker-0] statistician that consults with academia
and industry in experimental development.
[speaker-0] And he's a co-author to Quality by
Experimental Design, which is published by
Taylor
[speaker-0] and Francis. I wanted to add, like I said,
he's a great resource. He's a part of our
[speaker-0] spelling and autism community, but he's
also the lead developer and designer and a
[speaker-0] Don't know what the official title is,
Andrew, but that's cool app that was used
in
[speaker-0] that important research project at
University of Virginia that I want to talk
about
[speaker-0] in a little bit. welcome Andrew. Thanks.
Thanks for joining me. Hey, thank you for
[speaker-0] inviting me. I'm really stoked and glad to
be here today. So one of the things that
[speaker-0] we talk about, like I said, it's the
lighter side of the spectrum, but you
know, we
[speaker-0] were autism dads, right? And there's
something unique about
[speaker-0] being in that club and it certainly is a
club and a fraternity in many ways. But
[speaker-0] yeah, I think it's helpful to kind of get
a little background information. If you
[speaker-0] could kind of tell me briefly about your
journey and your son is Nicholas, right?
[speaker-0] And just why you can't tell us a little
bit about how old was he when he was
[speaker-0] diagnosed and kind of like, were those
early years like? Well, he was, he was
very
[speaker-0] young, like up until about
[speaker-0] six months, all the developmental
milestones were there. But then there was
a period
[speaker-0] where after nine months, ten months, we
start noticing him hand flapping a lot,
[speaker-0] doing things while in a seated position,
which we later on, it gets a label called
[speaker-0] stimming, not knowing that's what you
should give it.
[speaker-0] Flapping, they call it flapping. Exactly.
And delayed walking and whatnot. And I
[speaker-0] remember actually being at my ear and nose
doctor, his office, and they had this
[speaker-0] little pad of paper. And prior to this, by
the way, I should say we went into our
[speaker-0] family doctor and we said, this just looks
unusual. And he must be about 12 months
[speaker-0] by this time.
[speaker-0] And, um, and, uh, he had a bit of a rough
journey and w within a month of, of, of
[speaker-0] being born, had developed RSV, had to be
intubated. So he, he, days of life were
[speaker-0] quite rough. Yeah. But got through that
thankfully and everything. And then, uh,
the
[speaker-0] doctor basically said, oh, he's observing
the stimming and says, oh, he's a
[speaker-0] naturally excitable kid. Don't worry about
it.
[speaker-0] And then when I was at the ear and nose
throat specialist, saw this information
[speaker-0] flyer talking about autism and some of the
symptoms. That's when it started gluing
[speaker-0] in. You started kind of doing like a
mental check, like you're kind of like
check,
[speaker-0] check. Absolutely. And I'm like, hey, my
wife, Antoinette, but you know, like
[speaker-0] delayed speech, the stimming and all that
kind of stuff.
[speaker-0] And so we got referred to a developmental
pediatrician and by 18 months we had the
[speaker-0] diagnosis of autism. then everything after
that was history, right? What can we do
[speaker-0] to best support our child? Yeah. So it's
been a long, it's been a long journey. You
[speaker-0] caught it early on. then again, you kind
of started doing all the things that, uh,
[speaker-0] we're told to do, right? Like early
intervention and how important that is,
which
[speaker-0] obviously it is.
[speaker-0] And then so, kind of go through it then
education. What did they, you so, and I
just
[speaker-0] want to note, so you're actually in the
Toronto and the, was, you live in Toronto
[speaker-0] now, right? The Toronto area. Right. Yeah.
So this is all, so yeah, so experience
[speaker-0] might be slightly different, um, in terms
of resources and experience in Canada
[speaker-0] versus kind of what we do here in the
States. um, well, I would say they're
quite
[speaker-0] similar.
[speaker-0] Back in the day, was like, how do we get
our kid into ABA therapy as much as quick
[speaker-0] and fast as possible, right? And that's
what we did. We sought out the
psychologists
[speaker-0] that were experienced in autism, put a
program together for our kid. Where I
think
[speaker-0] our family's experiences maybe deviated a
little bit was...
[speaker-0] By training, I'm a researcher. So I will
do a literature search for all kinds of
[speaker-0] papers on autism, and I would do extensive
readings. And then I'd find out what the
[speaker-0] best evidence was out there that suggested
a type of therapy would be beneficial.
[speaker-0] And we would just start and try and do
things.
[speaker-0] that would be, um, would be helpful. And,
uh, and, and, uh, and a lot of it today
[speaker-0] explains, um, where our son is today. Um,
how so? Yeah. When you think about, people
[speaker-0] will talk about, uh, casein and gluten
free diets and, and, um, I go beyond that.
[speaker-0] Um, like why are certain diets recommended
and.
[speaker-0] And what you end up finding, and the
literature is getting up to speed in this
point
[speaker-0] here where they talk about the gut brain
act. And digestion is a really, really
[speaker-0] important concept for our kids. And they
often experience constipation issues and a
[speaker-0] variety of other issues. And at the end of
the day,
[speaker-0] Can you make it easier for them to digest
food? Yeah. And what you find is foods
[speaker-0] come in all different kinds of molecular
structures that have to get broken down
and
[speaker-0] then digested. Well, at the end of the
day, if you can give a diet to your kid
that
[speaker-0] consumes the... doesn't have to spend so
much time digesting, then they can absorb
[speaker-0] more nutrients more effectively. So case
in point in me, if I eat a pay to...
[speaker-0] plate of pasta, my body will be so busy
digesting, I'll go to sleep because
there's
[speaker-0] no energy. So when you look at our son
right now, I mean, I wish I had his
physique,
[speaker-0] but he looks like an Olympic swimmer. then
that kind of is philosophically, you
[speaker-0] can't cure the autism, at least there's no
cure for it. And should there even be
[speaker-0] one, right? Right.
[speaker-0] Um, some of the symptoms, you said, in
terms of, yeah, I don't mean to interrupt.
[speaker-0] was going back because I really love the
way you described the injury. was going to
[speaker-0] say, I wish I had, I wish doctors who
described it that well back when Stone was
[speaker-0] young and experienced knowing what we know
now, experiencing constipation pain,
[speaker-0] right? Like a lot of these things, like I
said, it it makes sense if you can digest
[speaker-0] and the reasons behind why do our kids
have these issues. That's kind of like.
[speaker-0] a different topic, but just understanding
and that, because I think, I don't know, I
[speaker-0] don't know what the thinking is today. I
know again, back when Stone was young, so
[speaker-0] we're looking about what, 10 to probably
12, 13 years ago when again, I first kind
[speaker-0] of discovered diet and learning about that
from naturopaths and research and my
[speaker-0] limited research. It was kind of just kind
of revolutionary. And like it just, was,
[speaker-0] and there were a lot, a lot of skeptics,
right? remember.
[speaker-0] Um, kind of scoring this appointment at
one of the leading local pediatricians
here.
[speaker-0] guy's supposed to be like, like one of the
nation's top experts in autism. And I got
[speaker-0] an appointment with him when I guess it's
still, was probably three or four. We had
[speaker-0] just kind of started, um, the gluten free
case and free diet. We're talking, he, he
[speaker-0] literally just stopped. He's just like,
[speaker-0] Well, if you think that's going to help,
okay, whatever. Wow. I've heard in his
[speaker-0] sense, uh, changed his tune. Fortunately
he's seen enough kiddos and all, but
[speaker-0] anyway, the point being like, think that
there were skeptics. don't know if there
[speaker-0] are still as many skeptics, if it's more
accepted today that this is like a real
[speaker-0] issue. Yeah. Oh no, it is. And, and I
think it highlights one of the issues, uh,
[speaker-0] about autism because
[speaker-0] When you try to look for issues that are
unrelated, let's say, to autism, it's very
[speaker-0] easy to use that label and brush it off
and say, oh, it's the autism. And then you
[speaker-0] ignore the other health issues because
you're trying to explain it away as the
[speaker-0] autism, right? And a lot of these kids of
ours, they have other underlying issues.
[speaker-0] The one today that stands out, which is my
[speaker-0] leads into my tip of the day is just the
whole movement and developmental
[speaker-0] coordination that since 2015 now is being
recognized as a core symptom of autism and
[speaker-0] that's motor impairment. And I could talk
about that for ad infinitum and why that's
[speaker-0] very important to address and something
that doesn't get taken into consideration
[speaker-0] these days.
[speaker-0] Um, with, uh, with a lot of our, with, uh,
a lot of our kids. Yeah, that's a really
[speaker-0] good point. And I think in a lot of ways,
kind of like some motor development, the
[speaker-0] role of motor, um, the role of the praxia,
all of those related issues are kind of
[speaker-0] still at the early stages in terms of, um,
acceptance and acknowledgement, right?
[speaker-0] The DSM, which is the standard that
doctors all use for
[speaker-0] diagnosing certain things. I believe the
2013 version finally acknowledged that you
[speaker-0] can have developmental coordination
disorder co-occurring with autism, which
is just
[speaker-0] the medical way of saying dyspraxia. then
I don't have to tell you about the
[speaker-0] wonderful work that Elizabeth Torres has
done out of Rutgers University.
[speaker-0] that has shown there's an impairment in
motor learning in our autistic kids. And
[speaker-0] that is so important to understand because
once you clue into it and realize it's an
[speaker-0] impairment, you can figure out how to
address it and really improve the quality
of
[speaker-0] life for our kids so that they can
experience things that they otherwise
would never
[speaker-0] have had.
[speaker-0] to experience. can give you a perfect
example of that. Yeah, I love examples. I
love
[speaker-0] stories. Well, when you think of it, when
you look at motor impairment and autism,
[speaker-0] the research that Dr. Torres has shown is
that these movements, when you're a
[speaker-0] typical people like you and I, we learn
how to make the future movement more
[speaker-0] efficient based on our prior movements.
[speaker-0] So when we learn to pick up a glass of
water, for example, my hand might come on
the
[speaker-0] top of it, my hand might slide down the
side, my first experience is with that
[speaker-0] glass. And then when I learn what grip is
comfortable and what makes it easier to
[speaker-0] lift and drink, then the future movement
emulates that. That mechanism in autism is
[speaker-0] impaired.
[speaker-0] and the impairment increases as the
diagnosis of autism increases in severity
as
[speaker-0] measured on an ADOS. So it means that this
kinematic learning in autism gets
[speaker-0] impaired. And this is the epiphany for me.
Right? Imagine what happens to social
[speaker-0] skills because as you age with your peer
group and instead of...
[speaker-0] sitting in a circle, talking about a book
and rolling a ball around when you're a
[speaker-0] toddler. Now you're playing soccer where
the level of kinematic skill in gross
motor
[speaker-0] and five motor is far more higher as age
or the demand is so much higher as age
[speaker-0] increases that our kiddos fall behind. And
then that impacts their social
[speaker-0] experiences. So, um, that's a great,
that's a great point. And to be clear too,
[speaker-0] also, I just want to add again for
[speaker-0] for listeners who aren't as familiar about
this. Again, this has nothing to do with
[speaker-0] cognitive abilities, is sometimes, right.
This is, but this is the mistake that,
[speaker-0] that so many make, right. Is that because
there's this disconnect in terms of the
[speaker-0] motor though, that, does impair other
areas in terms of communication and some
of
[speaker-0] these motor abilities, but they've been
fused together to say, oh, well they're
[speaker-0] just.
[speaker-0] developmentally disabled. You think about
every, that touches on an interesting
[speaker-0] study by a psychologist out in Montreal
who studied 40 autistic people. When you
[speaker-0] look at every test you can do to measure,
collect or whatever, it depends on motor
[speaker-0] skills. Right. Right. Everyone, like every
test. If the motor skills are impaired,
[speaker-0] then how do you expect to get an exact...
accurate results of the person's
[speaker-0] intelligence? It's difficult. So you have
to do things differently. And I wish
[speaker-0] today's academia field would recognize it
because they were faced with this problem
[speaker-0] in the 1930s and they solved it.
[speaker-0] And I don't know if you're aware of this,
David, but when you were coming into the
[speaker-0] United States at the start of the
industrial revolution, you needed labor.
Right.
[speaker-0] Well, a lot of these people couldn't speak
English. So how would you test them in
[speaker-0] the English language to know whether or
not they had the intellect to do certain
[speaker-0] types of jobs? Well, you had to, you had
to invent a different test that wasn't
[speaker-0] based on language. Oh, wow.
[speaker-0] And so those are called your Raven's
progressive matrices. And they've been
around
[speaker-0] since the 1930s. And so this researcher,
when she did that for these group of
[speaker-0] children that had impaired motor ability,
which they couldn't control the fine motor
[speaker-0] muscles in their mouth to speak. They
found that they lost their, their, uh,
[speaker-0] intellectual disability diagnosis. And so
why aren't we using those more? Well, I
[speaker-0] don't know.
[speaker-0] Honestly, don't know Is it just testing
bias or is it just one of those situations
[speaker-0] where the system's used to using these
other standardized tests? Yes, and that's
the
[speaker-0] thing because the community is, when I
mean the community, the people that want
to
[speaker-0] do these assessments want to know if the
tests have been normed against the certain
[speaker-0] population, right? So that you can compare
normative...
[speaker-0] values to the population to see where
things are. So when you invent these new
tests
[speaker-0] and you trial them on just a few people,
you got to push hundreds of subjects
[speaker-0] through this area. So you'll often hear
the term autism is very heterogeneous,
[speaker-0] right? So one of the things that prevents
us doing this in the area of autism is how
[speaker-0] do you partition
[speaker-0] autistic people in different buckets, like
maybe this group are, are, have some
[speaker-0] speaking ability and this group doesn't.
And because the group is so heterogeneous,
[speaker-0] they don't know how to create the
subpopulations to do these normative
tests. Right.
[speaker-0] So it gets very, very, very difficult. And
that's why they don't do it.
[speaker-0] But that kind of goes into the study out
of the University of Virginia and the
[speaker-0] innovative things we needed to do to test
literacy, for example, right? And I like
[speaker-0] to say autism doesn't care what your
education is. Right. If you have a PhD in
[speaker-0] education and the person with autism has a
neurological issue,
[speaker-0] that impairs the circuitry in the brain
that impacts motor. Well, then I should be
[speaker-0] talking to a neuroscientist, right? And so
you need a very diversified team of
[speaker-0] healthcare professionals, which thankfully
here in Canada with our son, I mean,
[speaker-0] we've got a fantastic medical team from
neurologists to neuroscientists to...
[speaker-0] developmental pediatricians and
ophthalmologists and all kinds of things
to support
[speaker-0] our kids. That's what they all need,
right? They do. And like you said, we've
talked
[speaker-0] about, that fortunately you do have that
team. Unfortunately, you've been in a
[speaker-0] position that you've been able to build
that team and support that team.
[speaker-0] Unfortunately, especially here in the U.S.
where the health care system in general,
[speaker-0] again, isn't as supportive, we'll say.
[speaker-0] I think that's really hard for a lot of
people to try to build that kind of a team
[speaker-0] anyway. is and even in Canada, don't get
me wrong, we have our issues up here. The
[speaker-0] parent really has to be, for lack of a
better word, pushy and not take no for an
[speaker-0] answer. think that's universal, Andrew. I
think we've learned that, right? that.
[speaker-0] Uh, and again, that's, that is kind of one
of the pieces of advice I'm always giving
[speaker-0] when asked or even when I'm not asked.
It's just, especially for parents and
younger
[speaker-0] kids who again, who've either just gotten
the diagnosis or starting school. I'm just
[speaker-0] like, you gotta be pushy. Like you said,
you gotta push because you're the
advocate.
[speaker-0] Like you're the one who's going to have to
make this happen because others won't.
[speaker-0] They're going to do what they need to do.
Whether it's the school system doing the
[speaker-0] bare minimum as you and I have both.
[speaker-0] at both experience. hope you're enjoying
the lighter side of the spectrum. So far
[speaker-0] we're commercial free, but if you're
finding value here, one way to support the
show
[speaker-0] is by considering me for speaking
engagement. I speak on unlocking
potential,
[speaker-0] whether it's for individuals like my son
or for entire organizations. I also offer
[speaker-0] fractional CMO services for businesses
needing strategic marketing support
without
[speaker-0] the full-time commitment, drawing on over
35 years of experience in marketing.
[speaker-0] My agency has helped companies and
healthcare practices increase their value,
grow,
[speaker-0] and even prepare for acquisition. To learn
more about my speaking topics, visit
[speaker-0] davidkoffer.com. Or if you're interested
in our marketing or fractional CMO
[speaker-0] services, check out kofermarketing.com. If
you're enjoying this episode, please
[speaker-0] leave a review. Your feedback means a lot
and it helps me make this podcast even
[speaker-0] more useful. Lastly, don't forget to share
it with anyone who would appreciate the
[speaker-0] insights and stories we're sharing here.
[speaker-0] Thanks again for listening.
[speaker-0] All of this stuff that I've just mentioned
about motor impairment. mean, what's the
[speaker-0] underlying good message out of all of that
stuff, right? And, and, in the case of
[speaker-0] our son, was like, well, it's winter. I
don't want to be indoors all day. I wonder
[speaker-0] if he can learn how to ski. Now, right
away, others will say, well, he's got
autism.
[speaker-0] There's no way we're going to be able to
come down a hill. Well, my son's been
doing
[speaker-0] it now for seven years. We just found a
great program.
[speaker-0] called track three and it's a disability.
It's a program to support kids with
[speaker-0] disabilities to learn how to ski. And so
they pair you up with a couple of ski
[speaker-0] instructors and they start on a bunny hill
and they teach you how to ski. Now my son
[speaker-0] goes to Glen Eden at the top of a, after
years on a bunny hill, he was
[speaker-0] going on the big hill and doing all his
best, S's all the way down the hill,
right?
[speaker-0] I love the videos. I remember you sharing
them last, last winter, right? Oh yeah,
[speaker-0] absolutely. I mean, I'm at the bottom. I'm
just rooting him like crazy. I'm happy as
[speaker-0] heck seeing that he can do something that
otherwise he wouldn't have had a chance at
[speaker-0] doing because nobody would presume the
competence, right? Right. Those programs
are
[speaker-0] gold. We're lucky enough to have something
similar here in the Seattle area, which
[speaker-0] is called Outdoors for All.
[speaker-0] Right. And they do that like it's a
skiing. Yeah. And they do a ski program.
has
[speaker-0] participated in that previously. It's been
a few years. He wants to do it again. So
[speaker-0] we're planning on doing that. They do
cycling, a lot of those things, right?
They're
[speaker-0] just wonderful programs for, for kids to
give them those, give them those
[speaker-0] opportunities, like you said. Yeah.
Absolutely. So like I said, we'd like to
have
[speaker-0] that little feature for the tip of the
week. You kind of touched on it a little
bit
[speaker-0] earlier. So let's go ahead.
[speaker-0] Let's see if producer Dave is ready for
the intro.
[speaker-0] All right. How's that for intro intro?
Absolutely love it. It's great. Uh, so
what
[speaker-0] you got for us? Well, it's presumed
competence and I, and I say that broadly.
Um,
[speaker-0] but you know, as your kids age, um, you
don't want them to be withheld from
[speaker-0] activities that everybody else can, can
participate in. So first get over that
[speaker-0] hurdle and assume they can do it.
[speaker-0] and then find the program that suits their
motor needs to actually be able to enjoy
[speaker-0] that program. Like cycling, for example. I
remember my son could ride a two-wheeler,
[speaker-0] but then turning was a bit of a hassle and
then he'd get dejected. Well, guess what?
[speaker-0] bought it. I got a tri-bite bent. Now he
can ride everything. can cruise around,
[speaker-0] right? Those are awesome. Do things and...
[speaker-0] Next year, we're going to get a tandem
bike and we're going to cruise together
[speaker-0] because at my age, I got to get exercise
and do some of that kind of stuff. And so
[speaker-0] get them into those activities that get
them to not only engage in those
activities
[speaker-0] other people do, but that gives them an
opportunity to also socialize. Right. I
[speaker-0] haven't found an autistic person that
hasn't been in a social environment and
have a
[speaker-0] sad face on. Right.
[speaker-0] And so I think get out there and and and
assume they enjoy those activities and
just
[speaker-0] are taken well Yeah, and again, I was just
gonna say that's another great point you
[speaker-0] make Andrew again in terms of social
activities again I think that one of the
false
[speaker-0] narratives that we had heard for so many
years and I even again I understood this
[speaker-0] was stone when he was younger as people
are like, oh, they're just not social
[speaker-0] Autistic people aren't social. I'm like,
well, how social would you be if you can't
[speaker-0] talk like?
[speaker-0] How social would you be if I dropped you
in the middle of Beijing tomorrow and
said,
[speaker-0] go, why don't you go hang out with these
people? You wouldn't want to do that.
[speaker-0] wouldn't know what the heck they're
saying. You wouldn't be able to, or maybe
you
[speaker-0] would figure it out quickly, but you
couldn't pick up the language. It's just,
[speaker-0] again, this, this assumption, this
societal bias, right? I've got a great
example of
[speaker-0] that. were at a picnic and there were,
there was a soccer pitch there.
[speaker-0] And Nicholas was a teenager at this time,
or maybe pre-teenager. And there was a
[speaker-0] group of kids playing soccer. And our son
was just sitting on the bench. All of a
[speaker-0] sudden, he gets up and he walks right into
the middle of that group.
[speaker-0] And everybody's like, well, Nicholas, get
out of the way or get on the bench. And I
[speaker-0] come back and I'm like, no, no, no, no,
no, no. He got up and he came in this
group
[speaker-0] for a reason. Yeah. And I'm telling you
that reason is he wants to participate.
[speaker-0] Don't tell me he's not wanting to be sold.
Right. That's inclusion right there. It's
[speaker-0] the motor that's preventing him from
kicking or passing a ball. So guess what
the
[speaker-0] group does? They adapt.
[speaker-0] And they start passing him the ball and he
stays at the center and he starts passing
[speaker-0] it to everybody else. And while he's doing
that, he's cracking the biggest smile on
[speaker-0] his face. those moments. is awesome.
Right. Oh, absolutely. Yeah, absolutely.
So
[speaker-0] like I mentioned earlier, so we kind of
met through the spelling community, right?
[speaker-0] And so you've, uh, you've been part of
that journey and we've shared lots of
[speaker-0] stories. But one of the things I think is
really cool is what you're doing.
[speaker-0] with Nicholas as an author. He's a book
author, right? He's published multiple
books
[speaker-0] now. Talk about that. Yeah, he's got the
third one and the coloring. He had this
[speaker-0] idea for a coloring book. Oh, I don't
think I'd heard about that. he wrote his
first
[speaker-0] book was... So he wrote a series on
Detective Nick and the first book was
called
[speaker-0] Detective Nick.
[speaker-0] case of the missing belly buttons. mean,
right there, come up with a title. I love
[speaker-0] it. then the next one was Detective Nick,
where did Mr. Creatures' cows go? And talk
[speaker-0] about the presumption of competence. It's
a story about cows that appreciate reading
[speaker-0] Shakespeare and can talk, but nobody
believes them.
[speaker-0] Oh wow. Perfect. And they all want to go
to the Howledge.
[speaker-0] I mean, how he comes up with this stuff,
make a poignant societal point just throws
[speaker-0] me. And then the other one just recently
this year was Detective Nick and the case,
[speaker-0] the mysterious case of the interstellar
beings. And so he's quite the little short
[speaker-0] kid's writer, which
[speaker-0] The story behind that is actually amazing.
don't know if you've ever read the Robert
[speaker-0] Munch. Robert Munch is like probably the
greatest selling children's author. the
[speaker-0] first book that he wrote was, Oh God, Love
You Much or something about how the
[speaker-0] mother takes care of the child. And then
when the mother becomes elderly, the child
[speaker-0] then takes care of the mother.
[speaker-0] And I'm sorry if I'm not remembering the
title, but yeah, he was an American who
[speaker-0] happens to now live in Guelph, Ontario,
which is the city not too far from where
we
[speaker-0] live. And so Nicholas loved his books and
he said, well, I want to be an author. I
[speaker-0] want to write some books. like, how do we,
do you think we can ask Robert Munch? And
[speaker-0] I'm like, well, let's.
[speaker-0] I guess so. says, yeah, like, why don't we
just send them a letter, dad? And so we
[speaker-0] did. And he responded. Oh, cool. So it was
all that's correct. And that was the
[speaker-0] motivation to, uh, to, to this wonderful
gentleman just sent the kind letter
[speaker-0] encouraging him to go forward and gave
them all kinds of tips on how to get the
book
[speaker-0] out there and whatnot. that's how we ended
up here today. Right.
[speaker-0] Yeah. You may have told me this before,
Andrew, but how, what was Nicholas's level
[speaker-0] of communication before spelling, before
he was introduced to the spelling
[speaker-0] methodology? um, is he reliable at all? he
have speak, how much speak? No, no, no.
[speaker-0] Uh, he, was, he was non-speaking. Yeah. I
mean, he had words here and there. And
[speaker-0] when he was upset and he really wanted to
communicate what he want, he could string
[speaker-0] out two or three words.
[speaker-0] But he was using sign language for period
of a time. so it never went further. I
[speaker-0] wouldn't say because of Nicholas. It was
very difficult for my wife and I to learn
[speaker-0] it because at the time, if you're an
autistic parent,
[speaker-0] Uh, and you don't have funding sources and
you're trying to get all this ABA help
[speaker-0] for your kids and just get them all the
supports that they need. You're, you're,
[speaker-0] you're paying for this out of pocket. I
remember you're paying for it. Plus the
[speaker-0] time, right? Like, that's the thing.
There's like bandwidth. remember it.
Sorry. I
[speaker-0] just like, cause I remember people saying
that to me are asking us that again, when
[speaker-0] Stone was young, they're like, well, why
don't you try, why don't you just try
[speaker-0] learning sign language?
[speaker-0] And I'm like, we're fricking drowning
here. right. mean, there's, there's the
very
[speaker-0] much that survival element, right? Okay.
We're, we're, we're focusing on the
lighter
[speaker-0] side, of course, which we want to do, but
the reality is that, um, man, it's just,
[speaker-0] you're, we're working, we're working all
the time. You said trying different
[speaker-0] therapies and.
[speaker-0] And then me and just still trying to be a
parent, like I said, and then you have
[speaker-0] another son that you're parenting as Stone
as a twin brother. Like, there's only so
[speaker-0] much that you can do also, I think, which
plays into it. Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. And
[speaker-0] that's why often, and I think I might've
even used this term with you, do you have
[speaker-0] the privilege of time? Right. And, uh, it
is a privilege without a doubt. Yeah, for
[speaker-0] sure. Absolutely.
[speaker-0] All right. So this, this is a good lead
and because we're talking about family and
[speaker-0] stresses and things like that. And then
again, something we've talked about. So
[speaker-0] let's go. This is for this is our fact or
fiction autism factor fiction segment. All
[speaker-0] right. See if, see if we have an intro for
that. Get quick time ready. And here we
[speaker-0] go. This is autism factor fiction. We're
breaking down what's real, what's rumor
and
[speaker-0] what might surprise you. Let's go. So, uh,
[speaker-0] That's that we're going to call her
Sabrina. Just I'm going to steal that from
[speaker-0] producer. Yeah. This is podcast. She's
she, he loaned her out to us from chat
GPT.
[speaker-0] But so for factor fiction, autism factor
fiction, one of the things I remember
[speaker-0] hearing early on was that, um, I've been
looking at if I have a great supportive
[speaker-0] wife, we've been married 27 years. I know
you in similar situation, but I don't know
[speaker-0] yet. You always hear that the divorce rate
is higher among couples with autistic.
[speaker-0] kids or special needs kids. yeah, that's
true. So you're okay. So you're going with
[speaker-0] fact. Yeah, I'm going with fact. Okay. So
at least again, according to, um, or AI, I
[speaker-0] hope I'm wrong. Yeah. So, well, okay. So
the belief in divorce rates are higher
[speaker-0] among couples with autistic children is
largely a myth.
[speaker-0] Research in the past decade has shown that
while parenting a child with autism does
[speaker-0] bring unique stressors, these couples do
not have a significantly higher divorce
[speaker-0] rate compared to parents with neurotypical
children. As a matter of fact, a 2010
[speaker-0] study from the Journal of Autism and
Developmental Disorders found that while
[speaker-0] parents of autistic children face distinct
challenges, their marriages are no more
[speaker-0] likely to end in divorce than other
marriages. In fact, some studies even
indicate
[speaker-0] the couples raising children with autism.
[speaker-0] may experience a stronger sense of
partnership and shared purpose, which can
have a
[speaker-0] stabilizing effect on the relationship. it
can strain relationships. I love that
[speaker-0] last part you just said, because when I
think about my wife, we are such a tag
team.
[speaker-0] don't know what we would do without each
other, right? Because that's how we make
it
[speaker-0] work, right?
[speaker-0] So I totally believe in that because that
shows up in our marriage. Yeah. think,
[speaker-0] yeah, same here. It's, it's it's a divide
and conquer, right? It's a partnership.
[speaker-0] It's you have to do, I think it's really
kind of the only way you make it work. And
[speaker-0] it requires that level of commitment to
the relationship, to the family, to
really,
[speaker-0] to really see that through. So I thought
that was really kind of interesting,
right?
[speaker-0] Cause
[speaker-0] I remember when I said early on, was like,
okay, as if we didn't have to worry about
[speaker-0] you're getting like these messages like,
well, good luck with that marriage now.
[speaker-0] Well, you know what? This is one of the,
when I'm being tested, I like to be right,
[speaker-0] but this is the first time I'm really glad
I'm wrong. Yeah. Well, like I said, it's,
[speaker-0] it's, again, a message of hope for, like I
said, the other parents out there, right?
[speaker-0] Who are, who may be challenging.
[speaker-0] Um, so like we were joking about this
before we started, we, there's so much
more to
[speaker-0] talk about. Um, and I want to get into
like, so there's going to be a part two or
[speaker-0] part three for sure. We'll bring you back.
But one of the things we talked about
[speaker-0] spelling and I've touched upon this, I'm
always going to be talking about it in
each
[speaker-0] of my podcasts because it's just, just
incredible journey with stone. But I
thought
[speaker-0] you had a really interesting observe
observation about how kind of comparing
the
[speaker-0] stages of spelling for parents.
[speaker-0] How similar to startups in a way, like, so
you talked about what the storming
[speaker-0] forming and norming, right? Yeah. Can you
talk about that a little bit and just kind
[speaker-0] of, again, how, how you've seen that kind
of play out, um, maybe in your own
[speaker-0] experience, but also again, you've, you've
talked to and become friends with a lot
[speaker-0] of other families. Well, once you, um,
you, you go down this path and you realize
[speaker-0] the world can open up.
[speaker-0] And what communication actually does for
you, you feel this kind of euphoria. is
[speaker-0] great. And so it's a natural high. But
then as time goes on, it's like, okay, how
am
[speaker-0] I going to sustain this? We need more
training. We got to develop the motor
skills.
[speaker-0] There's a kinematic learning process.
[speaker-0] there is so much more that we need to do
to now maintain this thing. Education,
[speaker-0] right? Like catching up on education.
mean, that's another, yeah. There's all of
[speaker-0] that stuff. so, and then even generalizing
to other people and giving the speller an
[speaker-0] opportunity to interact and work with
other people that know how to use the
[speaker-0] methodologies and whatnot to support the
needs of the speller.
[speaker-0] Um, and then you get to this, um, uh,
maturity point, um, it would kind of hit
home
[speaker-0] for us where I just turned 60, uh, and,
and my wife, uh, I'm not going to say what
[speaker-0] her age is because if she finds out,
she'll, but, um, um, what happens when
we're
[speaker-0] not here?
[speaker-0] They're going to live on, they're going to
keep on going. And so now the challenge
[speaker-0] is how to get them the motor support they
need to get to a point of some reliable
[speaker-0] way of independence so that they don't
have to depend on other people. Because
then
[speaker-0] it turns into that privilege of time. We
can afford the time now and give our son
[speaker-0] whatever he needs. But now we're thinking
about that next stage in life because I
[speaker-0] I could run around the block, it wouldn't
be an issue. Now walking is getting,
[speaker-0] you're feeling the age. You know what I
mean? Like your son's an adult, you're
[speaker-0] getting to be a senior. You can tell by
the color of my head, it's white. I've
been
[speaker-0] there for a while. And so you're slowing
down. I like to take naps in the
afternoon.
[speaker-0] Right? Right. Yeah. So changed. So yeah,
we change and we can't keep up with these
[speaker-0] kids. So how do you give them that level
of support when they're in their prime and
[speaker-0] you're not, right? So.
[speaker-0] That's some of the stuff that everybody is
going to go through and, and experience.
[speaker-0] And it's just like everything else. Right.
Yeah. Like it's just, it's just different
[speaker-0] stages. Right. And like I said, I thought
it was just a really keen observation
[speaker-0] because like I said, it's similar again,
what we went through it later. And I think
[speaker-0] that's the perfect word. Um, again, it's
euphoria, right? Like there's just
nothing,
[speaker-0] nothing like that. That the first time
spent the first time they're
communicating,
[speaker-0] like we hitting those milestones when
they, well, you, you, for what really
[speaker-0] bothers me is how autistic people are
emotionally treated. Right. When you
interact
[speaker-0] with another person through this unique
mode of communication called speech and
you
[speaker-0] can show your facial features and show the
emotions you're feeling and how that
[speaker-0] resonates with another person, if autistic
[speaker-0] folks aren't showing those emotions. That
doesn't mean they don't have them. But
[speaker-0] then what it means is the reciprocating
person develops a mindset of that person
and
[speaker-0] then preaches them more. I don't want to
say as a person just standing there in an
[speaker-0] inanimate object, but the level of
emotional appreciation is not there that
would be
[speaker-0] with the neuro-typical people.
[speaker-0] And this is what this beautiful form of
communication provides. It enhances love.
[speaker-0] Right? Yeah, it sure does. And so much of
that is missing from our society today.
[speaker-0] mean, so much of what we see in the news
is just, you know, um, yeah, lot of
[speaker-0] divisiveness, lot of... Yeah, absolutely.
And this is why I love autistic parents,
[speaker-0] because for me,
[speaker-0] A measure of love is the amount of time
and sacrifice and effort that people give
of
[speaker-0] themselves to other people. I mean,
there's only one reason why you do that.
You
[speaker-0] love your kids, right? And you want to
give them the best life possible. I love
[speaker-0] being immersed in that type of crowd
because I feel the love, right? Yeah.
[speaker-0] Yeah. Well, like, you know, we're, again,
it was so great that you and I had the
[speaker-0] opportunity to meet in person when you're
out here and your big, uh, your big family
[speaker-0] road trip, right? And just that, that,
that afternoon that we all got to spend
[speaker-0] together, the families and that was really
special for everyone. mean, Stone still
[speaker-0] talks about it and takes the pictures.
That was.
[speaker-0] Oh, and thank you for reminding me. got a
ton of pictures. haven't posted them yet.
[speaker-0] Oh, okay. I need do that. Right. I need
that privilege of time, but that's the
[speaker-0] reason why we flew the whole family from
Toronto over to Vancouver, went to
[speaker-0] Bellingham and then went to Seattle and
back again. Right. We just love the
[speaker-0] community out there. Every time I see you
guys advertising the, what is it? Beans
[speaker-0] and boards. Oh my gosh. I'm like, I wish I
could be there. Right.
[speaker-0] I can just imagine the love, the happiness
and joy that's going to be inside that
[speaker-0] crowd. It's a wonderful thing, right?
Yeah, no, you're absolutely right. And
that
[speaker-0] again, is another form of privilege too,
to have that opportunity. this is just a
[speaker-0] message that I'm going to continue to beat
on this podcast because frankly, for so
[speaker-0] long, I didn't have community when
Stone...
[speaker-0] was young, there wasn't, there weren't
Facebook groups, there weren't a lot.
They've
[speaker-0] come a long ways and it's just, so
valuable for mental health. And we know
that we,
[speaker-0] we need to have our mental health, right?
We need to be on our game to be there for
[speaker-0] our kids, whether they're, whether they're
kids or whether they're young adults.
[speaker-0] Yeah. And so I just really encourage
people to, you know, reach out and find
they're
[speaker-0] out there now. We know that all over
they're out there virtually and, and if
not
[speaker-0] person, try to, try to do it yourself.
Yeah.
[speaker-0] Yeah, absolutely. Absolutely. When my son
cracks a smile...
[speaker-0] It's a great day. I can feel it. I can
absolutely feel it. And so that's what I
want
[speaker-0] to return back to him and anybody else out
there, right? That we meet. Well, Andrew,
[speaker-0] like I said, we knew there's so much to
talk about. We're going to definitely have
[speaker-0] to do part two. Part two, I want to talk
about the study a little bit more, let
[speaker-0] people know about that. Cause I think
that's important. And the app again that
you
[speaker-0] created and some other things, but you
know, that we'll have to wait.
[speaker-0] for our next get together. But thank you
so much again for joining me. This has
been
[speaker-0] awesome. Oh no, I thoroughly enjoyed it.
Thank you for the opportunity and look
[speaker-0] forward to coming back again. Yeah, and
thank you audience members for joining us.
[speaker-0] Catch us next time on the lighter side of
the spectrum.